Guide to the New Day Films Archive, 1969-2018 RL.10180
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
New Day Films archive
1968-2018
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
New Day Films
RL.10180
44.5 Linear Feet 73 boxes; 36 film reels; 798 digital files
The New Day Films archive represents the activities of a feminist film-maker run cooperative founded in 1971, and spans the history of the organization to the present day. Materials include: analog elements as well as digital files for many of the cooperative's films dating from 1971 to the present; files assembled by individual co-founders Liane Brandon, Jim Klein, Julia Reichert, and Amalie R. Rothschild; correspondence between co-op members; records relating to film production and distribution; steering committee and annual meeting minutes; policies and other guidelines; reports on activities; fund-raising proposals; film sales and rental receipts; press mentions, articles, posters and other publicity; publications about New Day films such as brochures, catalogs, and magazines; and some photographs of events and members. Topics range widely and include women's studies, multiculturalism and diversity; social and political history; gender and socialization; media, culture; the environment; mental health; parenting and family; and global concerns. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Arrangement
The archive is arranged in the following series, which are further divided into subseries: Liane Brandon Co-Founder Files; Julia Reichert and Kim Klein Co-Founder Files; Amalie R. Rothschild Co-Founder Files; New Day Films Cooperative Files; New Day Films Printed Materials; Digital Films Collection; and Associated Digital Audiovisual Materials.
Historical Note
New Day Films is a United States filmmaker-run film distribution company that consists of more than 150 filmmakers. The company was founded in 1971 by four independent filmmakers in order to distribute their feminist films and to create a democratically run distribution cooperative. The co-founders are Liane Brandon, Jim Klein, Julia Reichert, and Amalie Rothschild. Their ground-breaking films about the lives of women were among the earliest of the emerging women's movement. As the co-operative has grown, New Day's titles now encompass a range of categories including women's studies, multiculturalism and diversity; social and political history; gender and socialization; media, culture; the environment: mental health; parenting and family; and global concerns. The company's titles have won an Academy Award, Emmy Awards, Academy Award nominations and hundreds of awards at film festivals. Their films have been broadcast on PBS, HBO and other national networks.
Conditions Governing Access
The New Day Films Cooperative Files series files are closed to use until 2025; all other series are open.
Audiovisual media such as film reels and optical disks are closed to use; access copies may be requested in advance.
Please contact the Rubenstein Library before coming to use this collection.
Provenance
The New Day Films archive was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift from 2013-2019. The material in this collection was donated by Liane Brandon and Amalie R. Rothschild.
Collection Overview
The New Day Films archive represents the activities of the feminist film-maker run cooperative founded in 1971, and spans the history of the organization to the present day. Their ground-breaking films about the lives of women were among the earliest of the emerging women's movement. Materials include: files assembled by individual co-founders Liane Brandon, Jim Klein, Julia Reichert, and Amalie Rothschild; correspondence between co-op members; records relating to film production and distribution; steering committee and annual meeting minutes; conference call minutes; policies and other guidelines; reports on activities; fund-raising proposals; film rental receipts; press articles, posters and other publicity; publications about New Day films such as pamphlets, catalogs, and magazines; and photographs of events and members.
Analog elements and digital versions for many of the co-founder's films form an important part of the collection and relate to these seminal feminist film titles: Woo Who? May Wilson (Rothschild, 1969);Sometimes I Wonder Who I Am (Brandon, 1970); Anything You Want to Be (Brandon, 1971); Growing up Female (Klein, Reichert, 1971); Betty Tells Her Story (Brandon, 1972); It Happens to Us (Rothschild, 1972); Nana, Mom, and Me (Rothschild, 1974); and Not So Young Now As Then (Brandon, 1974). Another central piece of the collection are the 214 born-digital film files representing 103 filmmakers who form the New Day cooperative.
Topics explored in the New Day films and other materials range widely, and include but are not limited to: women's studies; multiculturalism and diversity; social and political histories; gender and socialization; media culture; the environment; mental health; parenting and family; and global concerns such as immigration and labor.
The materials in this collection were donated by Liane Brandon and Amalie R. Rothschild, and were acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Documentary films -- Production and direction; Documentary films -- United States -- Distribution; Feminism -- United States -- History; Feminism and art -- United States; Feminism and motion pictures -- United States; Feminist films -- United States; Motion pictures -- Social aspects; Motion pictures -- United States -- Production and direction; Women artists -- United States; Women in the motion picture industry -- United States; Women motion picture producers and directors -- United States; Audiovisual materials; Color films (visual works); 16mm; Digital images; Digital moving image formats; Optical disks; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University); Brandon, Liane; Rothschild, Amalie R.; Reichert, Julia; Klein, Jim, 1948-; Abt, Emily; Anderson, Kelly; Argueta, Luis; Arnold, Robert,, 1966-; Avila-Hanna, Brenda; Beraza, Suzan; Booth, Marlene,, 1948-; Liem, Deann Borshay; Bouvrie, Alice Dungan; Brashear, Regan Pretlow; March, Briar; Brodsky, Ellen; Bruno, Ellen; Burstein, Cindy; Bush, Annie; Chasnoff, Debra,, 1957-2017; Chiang, S. Leo; Cohn, Peter,, 1955-; Cool, Jenny; Courtney, Heather; Dater, Alan; Davenport, Reid (Filmmaker); Davis, Erin (Filmmaker); Dorosh-Walther, Blair; Dwyer, Alicia; Elliott, Alice; Entine, Sarah; Epperlein, Karina; Farinella, Samantha; Ferrero, Pat,, 1942-; Fishel, Deirdre; Frankenstein, Ellen; Frick, Ellen; Friedman, Bonnie; Garrison, Andrew; Gilomen, Jennifer; Ginzberg, Abby; Goldman, Michal; Goldsmith, Rick; Gold, Tami; Gossels, Lisa; Green, Cheryl, (Filmmaker); Herold, Kara; Herring, Christie; Hershfield, Joanne, 1950-; Hessman, Robin; Hill, Isabel,, 1951-; Huang, Kathy; Jennings, Katie; Jensen, J. Christian; Kaneko, Ann; Kantayya, Shalini; Khan, Sofian; Lagarde, Charlotte; Leland, Andrea E.; Lieff, Judy; Lipman, Mark, (Documentary filmmaker); Logsdon, Dawn; Lung, Robin; Mandelbaum, Juan; Mondell, Cynthia Salzman; Nkara, Frances; Ochs, Jacki; Ohama, Corey; Onís, Paco de; O'Rourke, Shannon; Pennick, Faith; Raval, P. J. ((Paul James)); Redfearn, Jennifer; Richter, Robert,, 1929-; Rigby, Theo; Rosenstein, Jay; Sartain, Sophie; Schiller, Greta; Seckinger, Beverly; Skurnik, Jonathan; Smith, Tommie Dell (Filmmaker); Son, Mina T.; Stern, Susan, (Filmmaker); Sterrenberg, Jay Arthur; Syjuco, Marty; Symons, Johnny; Thompson, Shirley,, 1963-; Walton, Pam; Yates, Pamela; Shaffer, Deborah
- Liane Brandon, New Day Films Co-Founder Files, 1970-2014; 14.0 Linear Feet 24 boxes (mss.); 6 film reels (1 box); 6 optical and video disks; 1 audio CD; 5 digital files (.mp4s, .mov, .iso)
  Scope and Contents
  Files in this series pertain to the career of filmmaker and New Day Films co-founder Liane Brandon, and her activities on behalf of New Day from its beginnings to the present day. The materials are organized accordingly in two divisions that reflect these closely interwoven aspects of her professional life.
  The series is organized first by subseries representing each of Brandon's films distributed by New Day; each film project subseries comprises original analog film elements, digital versions of the film and other digital elements, and includes supporting materials - in some cases quite extensive - documenting the evolution and production of the film projects as well as the life of the films after their release.
  The final subseries is the New Day cooperative files maintained by Brandon for her own use. These papers reveal the central role she had in the organization's founding and in its continued growth into the 1980s. The files contain many items of correspondence, planning and meeting notes, and many other items, arranged in chronological order. There are many other documents pertaining to Brandon's work on behalf of New Day Films in the main New Day Cooperative Files series, particularly in the Steering Committee records.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Original audiovisual media are closed to use; access copies are available with advance notice. Please contact the Rubenstein Library before coming to use this collection.
  - Films and Film Project Papers, 1970-2014; 11 Linear Feet 19 boxes (mss.); 6 film reels (1 box); 6 optical and video disks; 5 digital files (.mp4s, .mov, .iso)
    These films by Liane Brandon, New Day Films co-founder, are among the most well-known of the mid-20th century feminist movement: Anything You Want To Be (1972), Betty Tells Her Story (1972), and Sometimes I Wonder Who I Am (1970). Later works include Once Upon A Choice (1980) and How To Prevent A Nuclear War (1987).
    The film series are organized in alphabetical order by title, and each begins with audiovisual media series of original analog components (restricted access) and in most cases, digital derivates and access copies. The papers associated with Brandon's film projects are arranged in their original functional groupings: Financials; Production; Publicity/Press; and Screenings. There are additional subgroups when needed. These materials provide rich documentation on the planning and direction of each film project, and the films' reception and audience. The largest series are for Betty Tells Her Story, Once Upon a Choice, and How to Prevent and Nuclear War.
    Sales and rental invoices for these films, gathered into their own subseries, document in detail the wide variety of entities - women's groups, public libraries, colleges and universities, women's health and mental wellness clinics, and corporate organizations - who requested copies of these films over the years.
    - Anything You Want to Be (1971), 1970-2014; Total running time: 00:08:00
      The film series begins with analog film components and digital verson of film. Folders in the Papers subseries are arranged in alphabetical order by folder title.
      Additional materials related to Anything You Want To Be include publicity and press mentions, found chiefly in the Liane Brandon/Films/General series, and in the New Day Films Cooperative publicity and print materials files. Some of the latest dates in the collection refer to retrospective women's film festivals where Anything You Want To Be and other films were shown.
      Film Overview
      Anything You Want To Be was one of the earliest and most popular films of the Women's Movement. Released in 1971, this groundbreaking film about a teenager's humorous collision with gender role stereotypes was one of the first to explore the external pressures and the more subtle, internal pressures a girl faces in finding her identity. In a series of comical vignettes, a bright high school girl finds that, despite her parents' assurance that she can be "anything she wants to be," she is repeatedly foiled by social expectations and media stereotypes. Anything You Want To Be is a founding film of New Day Films.
      - Audiovisual Resources, 1971; 6 film reels; 1 optical disk; 1 mp4 file
        - Anything You Want To Be, digital movie, 1971; 00:08:00 (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0001_u, Video-file BrandonLiane_AnythingYouWantToBe.mp4)
        - Anything You Want To Be, A Roll B&W Rev. Orig., 1971; 300 film ft. (Box AV-01, Film-reel RL10180-F16-0012)
        - Anything You Want To Be, B Roll B&W Rev. Orig., 1971; 300 film ft. (Box AV-01, Film-reel RL10180-F16-0013)
        - Anything You Want To Be, 16mm mixed mag soundtrack, 1971; 300 film ft. (Box AV-01, Film-reel RL10180-F16-0014)
        - Anything You Want To Be, dupe negative, 1971; 300 film ft. (Box AV-01, Film-reel RL10180-F16-0015)
        - Anything You Want To Be, BW DN for BW sound print, 1971; 300 film ft. (Box AV-01, Film-reel RL10180-F16-0016)
        - Anything You Want To Be, 16mm B&W sound release print, 1971; 300 film ft. (Box AV-01, Film-reel RL10180-F16-0017)
        - Anything You Want To Be, 1971; 00:08:00 (Box AV-07, Optical-disc RL10180-DVD-0002)
      - Papers, 1970-1984, 2011-2014
        These and similar subseries in the filmmakers' series (Brandon and Rothschild) contain the files of paper records associated with each film production project, and often contain post-production related events and publicity. Arranged in alphabetical order by folder title.
        - Articles, 1971-1978 (Box 1)
        - Articles: Lawsuits - University of California/Berkeley, AT&T, 1977-1984 (Box 1)
        - Correspondence: Email from Sandy Jabaily with reminiscences about film, 2012 (Box 1)
          Reminisces about the film, her reaction to it after viewing it again after many decades, and changes in current society.
        - Financials: Grants, not funded, 1970-1971 (Box 1)
        - Production: Notes, 1970-1971 (Box 1)
        - Production: Lab work, shipping cases, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
        - Publicity/Press, 1971-1979 and undated (Box 1)
          Includes set of still photographs of protagonist.
        - Screenings, 1971-1980, 2011-2014; 3 folders (Box 1)
          The first two folders contain correspondence and publicity relating to earlier film festival screenings; the third folder contains materials from later screenings.
    - Betty Tells Her Story (1972), 1971-2013; Total running time: 00:20:00
      Series contains analog film components and digital version of film. Papers related to the film project are arranged in these subgroups: Articles, Correspondence, Financials, Production, Publicity/Press, and Screenings.
      Additional materials related to Betty Tells Her Story are found chiefly in publicity files in the Liane Brandon/Films/General series, and in the New Day Films Cooperative publicity and print materials files. Some of the latest dates in the collection refer to retrospective women's film festivals where "Betty" and other Brandon films were shown.
      Betty Tells Her Story was the first independent film of the women's movement to explore the issues of body image, self-worth and beauty in our culture. The story and Betty are witty and engaging and offer insights into the ways clothing and appearance affect a woman's identity.
      The story Betty tells is a simple one. She needed "the perfect dress" for a special occasion. Betty describes in amusing detail how she found just the right one, spent more than she could afford for it, modeled it for admiring friends, felt absolutely transformed and then...never got to wear it. The film received a great deal of positive attention when it was released, and went on to become a cult classic. It is still viewed today as part of discussions about women's body image and identity.
      - Audiovisual resources, 1972
        - Betty Tells Her Story, digital movie, 1972; 00:20:00 (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0001_u, Video-file BrandonLiane_BettyTellsHerStory.mp4)
        - Betty Tells Her Story, 1972; 00:20:00 (Box AV-07, Video-disc RL10180-DVD-0006)
      - Papers, 1971-2013
        - Articles, 1972-2004; 2 folders (Box 2)
          Includes an article by E. Mishler, Harvard Medical School, Historians of the self.... Reviews appear in The second wave: a magazine of new feminism, Videosociology (Chandra Hecht), and various film studies and association journals/newsletters.
        - Correspondence: Letters, cards, emails from and about Betty Murray, the original "Betty", 1987-2010 (Box 2)
          Includes Betty Murray's obituary.
        - Financials: The Learning Channel contract, 1991-1992 (Box 2)
        - Production: Grant and production notes, 1971-2003 (Box 2)
        - Production: Film lab records, 1988-1989, 1991 (Box 2)
        - Publicity/Press: Reviews, 1972-1999 and undated (Box 2)
        - Oversize scrapbook pages (4) with clippings of reviews and handwritten comment slips, 1971-1976; Four black paper pages measure approximately 9x12 inches. (Box 64)
        - Publicity/Press: General, 1973-1982 and undated (Box 2)
        - Publicity/Press: National Film Registry, 1999 (Box 2)
        - Screenings: Festivals and conferences, 1972-2013 and undated; folders 1-2 of 3 (Box 2)
          Fliers, programs, and packets originate from Boston-area festivals and conferences, and from locations around the country. The most recent screening publicity announces a 2013 panel discussion on body image at Simmons College.
        - Screenings: Festivals and conferences, 1972-2013 and undated; folder 3 of 3 (Box 3)
        - Screenings: Coolidge Corner Movie House, Brookline, Mass., small poster with film screenings calendar, after 1972 (Box 65)
        - Oversize posters for film screenings, after 1974, 1984 (Box 66)
    - How to Prevent a Nuclear War (1987), 1979-2004; Total running time: 00:30:00
      This film series begins with analog film elements and a digital version of the film. Papers and other supporting materials are extensive, and are arranged in these subgroups: Financials, Production, Publicity/Press, and Screenings. Within subgroups, folders are arranged in chronological order.
      How to Prevent a Nuclear War was released in 1987 to wide acclaim. Featured in fifteen vignettes are activists of all types, including a suburban housewife who stuffs pamphlets in the pockets of fellow skiers while riding the ski lift, a group of small town citizens who visit their congressman, a woman serving on the Boston School Committee, a shipyard welder, a high school student attending her high school's "Picnic for Peace," a flight attendant, and the founder of an inner city gospel choir, Vernon Jones, who conducts the "Concert for Peace," a key scene in the film. A central performer in other scenes is comedian and songwriter Tom Lehrer, who composed (and sings) the film's parodic theme song, "We'll All Go Together When We Go."
      - Audiovisual Resources, 1987
        - How to Prevent a Nuclear War, digital movie, 1987 (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0001_u, Video-file BrandonLiane_HowToPreventANuclearWar.mp4)
        - How to Prevent a Nuclear War, 1987; 00:31:43 (Box AV-07, Video-disc RL10180-DVD-0001)
      - Papers, 1979-2004
        - Financials, 1979-1996
          - Boston Film and Video sponsorship correspondence and agreement, 1979, 1986-1987 (Box 3)
            1979 date refers to Boston Film and Video's original IRS certificate of exemption.
          - Peace Development fund, 1982 (Box 3)
          - Fundraising party flier, 1983 June 26 (Box 3)
          - Tom Lehrer shoot receipts, 1984 November 01-1984 December 31 (Box 3)
          - Fundraising parties, concert, correspondence, 1984-1988 (Box 3)
          - Fundraising/grants, 1984-1988 (Box 3)
          - DuArt Film Laboratories service invoices and correspondence, 1984-1996 (Box 3)
          - Production and post-production budget drafts, 1985 (Box 3)
            Contains three drafts of lengthy film production budget proposals; packets include photocopies of press and publicity.
          - The Communicators (Boston) sponsorship correspondence and agreement, 1985-1986 (Box 3)
        - Production, circa 1983-2004
          Production files for this film are extensive and reveal the amount of effort and funding that went into the film. Files related to specific scene shoots, many of which were filmed interviews, often include: production schedules; lists of players and crew; interview notes and cue cards; correspondences; and notes. In some cases there are color snapshots of interviewees and interiors where they were interviewed. Dates often refer to the shoot date, and may contain materials with earlier and later dates. The end date of 2004 derives from correspondence sent to Brandon following the passing of the 1988 "Concert for Peace" chorus leader, Vernon Jones.
          - Early film research and plans, circa 1983 (Box 3)
          - Contacts and interviewees, 1983-1984 (Box 3)
          - Nick Carter (from SANE/FREEZE) interview and shoot, 1983-1984 (Box 3)
            Includes 1983 sermon transcript, 1984 church service program, and interview cards.
          - Run for Peace, Cambridge, Mass. shoot, 1984 April 1 (Box 3)
            Includes publicity for the run and correspondence from sponsor Au Bon Pain executives.
          - Vivian Day and Tony Crayton shoot, 1984 June 9 (Box 4)
          - Bill Wimpisinger shoot, 1984 July 5 (Box 4)
          - Natick (Mass.) Peace Vigil and Doc Miller shoots, 1984 July 10, 1990 February 19 (Box 4)
            The Natick, Massachusetts Peace Vigil is an activist group that organized during the 1980s.
          - Betty Tuttle shoot, 1984 July 15 (Box 4)
          - Recording session and contacts, 1984 October 15 (Box 4)
          - Tom Lehrer shoot: budgets, rehearsals, and expense reports, 1984 November 1-January 31 (Box 4)
          - Tom Lehrer shoot, Strand Theater, Dorchester, Mass., production materials, 1984 December 01-1984 December 31 (Box 4)
            Includes lyrics and music sheets for Lehrer's composition, We Will All Go Together When We Go. Also includes props lists, contacts, extensive scheduling, and some photographs of props. Includes some correspondence with singer Pamela Bierly.
          - Natick, Massachusetts 4th of July Parade shoot, 1984-1985 (Box 4)
            Production schedule, local anti-nuke group newsletters, information about the Peace Vigil, and other materials.
          - Film labs and film stock inventories, 1984-1987 (Box 4)
          - Film lab order forms and reports, 1984-1987 (Box 5)
          - Signed releases from performers and interviewees, 1984-1987 (Box 4)
          - Natick Peace Vigil and interviews, Lynn Worth's, 1985 April 1-May 31 (Box 4)
          - Jenny Godley, high school "Picnic for Peace" shoot, 1985 May 19 (Box 4)
          - Phil Morrison, Gary Helfrien, Dennis Minihane shoots, 1985 July-August (Box 4)
          - Republican Representative Silvo Conte shoot, Pittsfield, Mass., 1985 August 24 (Box 4)
          - Deen Leonard, Steve Meecham, Gary Helfrich shoots at airport and General Dynamics, 1985 September 30 (Box 5)
          - Tom Lehrer interview/shoot, 1985 November 1-November 30 (Box 5)
            Contains two pieces: a letter from Brandon to Lehrer, and a schedule.
          - Gospel concert, Vernon Jones Singers and New Life Choir correspondence, 1985-2004 (Box 5)
            End date of 2004 derives from correspondence following the passing of chorus leader Vernon Jones.
          - Juanita Wade (Boston School Committee member) shoots in Boston and at Aswalos House, Dorchester, 1986 March 3 and August 7 (Box 5)
          - Editing notes, 1986 (Box 5)
          - Gospel Concert for Peace - Vernon Jones Singers, shoot in Cambridge, 1986 May (Box 5)
          - Gospel Concert for Peace, 1986 June and 2004 (Box 5)
            Includes 2004 correspondence following the passing away of chorus leader Vernon Jones.
          - Olin Hayes narrative script, Natick Peace Vigil anniversary, 1987 January-1990 October (Box 5)